Michael McClure Papers
Michael McClure Papers
1956-1964
McClure, Michael.
41 items (SC)
Papers of the American poet, playwright, essayist, novelist. Born 1932. Letters to Carol Bergé, Diane Di Prima, LeRoi Jones, and Alan Marlowe; typescript poems; and a holograph script for The Blossom; or, Billy the Kid, with a holograph introduction dated Mar. 28, 1962.
149240
Biographical History
Michael McClure was an American poet, playwright, essayist, and novelist. Born in 1932 in Marysville, Kansas, McClure attended Wichita State University (1951-1953) and the University of Arizona (1953-1954) but received his B.A. from San Francisco State College in 1955.
McClure taught at the California College of Arts and Crafts in Oakland, first as assistant professor (1962-1977) and then as associate professor (1977) and finally professor of humanities. He spent a year as lecturer at the State University of New York at Buffalo (1979) before accepting a position as associate fellow at Pierson College, Yale University (1982). He also served on the board of directors of the Drylands Institute, an environmental research organization in Tucson, Arizona.
He is the author of more than forty collections of poetry, with translations of his work into has been translated into German, French, and Yugoslavian.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Michael McClure Papers consist of correspondence and writings. Correspondence, with the exception of a single item from Carol Berge, is outgoing; the bulk relates to McClure's contributions to the literary journal Floating Bear (Diane di Prima) and the American Theatre for Poets (Alan Marlowe). Writings includes poetry and a play entitled The Blossom, or, Billy the Kid.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Radicalism; Baraka, Imamu Amiri, 1934-; Bergé, Carol, 1928-; Di Prima, Diane.; Doyle, Kirby.; Marlowe, Alan.; McClure, Michael.; The Blossom; or, Billy the Kid.; American literature -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Bohemianism -- United States.; Dramatists, American -- 20th century.; Literature, Experimental.; Poets, American.; Letters (correspondence); Poems.; Scripts (documents); Dramatists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Baraka, Imamu Amiri (LeRoi Jones), 1959-1963; 14 items (Sc 23)
  - Berge, Carol, Jan 1962; 2 items (Sc 23)
  - di Prima, Diane, 1962-1964; 2 items (Sc 23)
  - Doyle, Kirby, 4 Aug 1964; 1 item (Sc 23)
  - Linnich, Billy, 9 Dec 1963; 1 item (Sc 23)
  - Marlowe, Alan, 1963-1964; undated; 8 items (Sc 23)
- Writings
  - "The Blossom, or, Billy the Kid", 28 Mar 1962; play, with holograph preface (Sc 23)
  - "Canticle", undated; poem (Sc 23)
  - "Hymns to St. Geryon", undated; poems (Sc 23)
  - "Passage", undated; holograph poems; "Published 1956 by J. Williams" (Sc 23)
  - "Poisoned Wheat", undated; typescript poem with pencil corrections (Sc 23)
  - "Reason", 1963; typescript with holograph corrections (Sc 23)
  - "The Robe", undated; poem (Sc 23)